ILGWU Communications Department Records 5780/176
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Communications Department Records
1936-2001
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)
5780/176
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Files, records (documents).
Consists of alphabetical subject files maintained by the Communications Department.
6323079
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
C. Berne, July 28, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 15, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The precursor to the ILGWU's Communications Department was the Publications and Publicity Department. Though the name and scope of the department changed over time, its primary function stayed the same throughout the history of the ILGWU. The department was responsible for the publication of the ILGWU's official publication Justice, as well as the official editions in Yiddish (Gerechtigkeit), Italian (Giustizia), and Spanish (Justicia), and it was also responsible for cooperating with journalists outside of the union on pieces about the ILGWU. Beyond coordinating such efforts of journalists, the Communications Department provided information about the union to other labor organizations, students, and teachers.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Communications Department consist entirely of subject and biographical files, with related photographs. Taken together, these records document ILGWU events, organizations, and leaders, as well as political figures and other prominent labor unionists.
The Communications Department's alphabetical subject files (5780/176) contain clippings from publications that appear to be produced through the Communications Department or with its cooperation. The clippings in this collection provide concise, published accounts of events and affiliates of the ILGWU, as well as of issues of special interest to the union. The related photograph collection (5780/176 P) includes a variety of images documenting the work of the union, arranged in two series: Events and Organizations, and Personalities. These photographs include large groups of people at meetings, protests, and other events, and ILGWU members, staff, and leaders at work.
The Communications Department's biographical files (5780/177) are of interest not only because they provide sometimes difficult-to-find, basic information on ILGWU members and officers, but because that information was provided by the individuals themselves, on forms provided by the union and designed to be returned to the office when completed. These biographical forms appear to have begun as a project of the editors of Justice, and the information contained includes date and place of birth, when the subject arrived in the United States, positions held in the ILGWU or other unions, and outside activities and interests. The related photograph collection (5780/177 P) includes portraits of some of the individuals represented in the biographical files, as well as photographs of events and miscellaneous photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/176 P: ILGWU Communications Department Photographs 5780/177: ILGWU Communications Department Biography Files 5780/177 P: ILGWU Communications Department Biography File Photographs
Women's clothing industry--New York (State)--New York; Women's clothing industry--United States.; Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State)- -New York; Clothing workers--Labor unions--United States.; Clothing workers--New York (State)--New York; Clothing workers--United States.; Textile workers--New York (State)--New York; Textile workers--United States.; Industrial relations--New York (State); Industrial relations--United States.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Communications Dept.
6323079
- AFL-CIO News Clippings, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- APALA News Clippings, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Alliance of Asian Pacific Labor (APALA), 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ILGWU Archives, 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Associate Membership (AIM), 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Benefits Fund, 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Benefits - General, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Campaign for Justice, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Classic Coat Article, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Bill Clinton Articles, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW), 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Consumer, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Contract Negotiations, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Contract Negotiation, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Council on American Fashion, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Convention Clippings, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Convention Clippings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Convention Clippings, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Cutting Edge, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Day Care, 1987-1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Dear Justice, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Dukakis Clippings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Earned Income Credit, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Education - General, 1989-1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Report to the Education Committee of the GEB, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- ESL Program, 1987-1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Ellis Island Memories, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- English as a Second Language (ESL), 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Essay Contest, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Garment Industry Development, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Garment Center Zoning, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Garment Workers and Whole Lot More, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Miscellaneous, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Office - General, 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- General Articles, 1987-1994 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- General Advisory, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- General Executive Board, 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Health Center Administration, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Health Care Reform, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Health and Consumer Columns, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Health and Safety, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- History in the Making, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Homework, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- House Calls, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- ILGWU History, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Immigration Project, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- International Relations, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Labor Day Parade, 1987-1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Labor - General, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Labor Law Reform, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Labor History, 1986-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Leaders on the Line, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Legal Department, 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Legislative - General, 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Letters, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Workers and Whole Lot More, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Local 10, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Local 23-25, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Local 62-32, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Local 66-40, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Local 89-22-1, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Local 91-105, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Local 132-98-102, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Local 155, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Members Assistant Program (MAP), 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Jay Mazur, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Media Matters, 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Merger, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Metro Organizing, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Negotiations - General, 1988-1994 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- New York State Region, 1986-1992 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Organizing, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Organization and Field Development, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Obituary, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- PACE, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Political Department, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- President's Column, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Promotion and Advertising, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Retiree Services, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Recipes, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Canada, 1986-1993 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Central States Region, 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Eastern Pennsylvania Region, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Midwest Region, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- New England Region, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- New Jersey Region, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Northeast Department, 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Puerto Rico, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Southeast Region, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Upper South Department, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Western States, 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Research Department, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Retirees After 1992, 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Retirees - General, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Retirees, 1991-1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Retirees, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Retirees, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Retirees, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Retirees, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Retirees, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Scholarships, 1986-1994 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Solidarity, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Solidarity Day, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- South Africa, 1986-1993 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Statue of Liberty, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Sweatshops, 1986-1995 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Trade - General, 1986-1994 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Triangle Fire, 1986-1995 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Union Health Center, 1986-1995 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Union Label, 1987-1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Union Privilege, 1987-1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Unity House, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Warehouse Workers, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Washington Watch, 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Women's Issues, 1986-1992 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Justice Clippings - Kellwood, 1965-1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Labor History Articles, 1936-1992 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Labor Day History, 1936-2001 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Monarch Fire, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Women's History Articles, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 29)